Guide to the Nancy Cunard Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nancy Cunard collection
1930-1965
GEN MSS 438
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box) + 1 portfolio
Collection contains correspondence, writings and other materials by or related to Nancy Cunard. Correspondence includes letters from Cunard to Miriam J. Benkovitz (biographer and bibliographer of Ronald Firbank), Jinadasa Vijayatunga, and others, as well as letters to Cunard from John Robertson Scott. Writings include typescript and holograph poems and articles by Cunard, and translations of poems by "Geraldine" and Neftalí Beltrán. Also included is a typescript memoir about Cunard by Iris Tree entitled "We Shall Not Forget."
Cunard, Nancy, 1896-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Portfolio (folders 36-41): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
NANCY CUNARD (1896-1965)
Nancy Cunard was born on 10 March 1896 in Nevill Holt, Leicestershire, England, daughter of Sir Bache Cunard and Lady Maud Alice Burke Cunard. She spent her childhood as part of the British upper class on the family estate, surrounded by her parents' literary and artistic friends. When Cunard was fourteen, she moved with her mother to London, and subsequently attended schools in London, Paris and Germany.
Cunard began writing and publishing poetry in the 1910's, and after World War I she settled in Paris, where she became involved in the Dada, Surrealist and Modernist movements. Her first volume of poetry, Outlaws, was published in 1921, followed in 1923 by Sublunary and Parallax in 1925.
In 1927 Cunard founded the Hours Press in an old farmhouse in La Chapelle-Réanville, Normandy. The Press specialized in publishing writers whose works had difficulty finding a home elsewhere, including Ezra Pound and Samuel Beckett. The Hours Press closed after four years, after which Cunard became intensely involved in the black civil rights movement in the United States. Driven by her interest in the struggle, she spent several years collecting writings by and about African-Americans, which were published in 1934 in the anthology Negro.
For most of 1936-1939 Cunard lived in Madrid with the poet Pablo Neruda, working as a freelance writer during the Spanish Civil War. She spent most of World War II in London, where she published the anthology Poems for France (1944). After the war, Cunard returned to France to find that the Germans had destroyed or stolen most of her possessions.
Cunard's later publications included Grand Man: Memories of Norman Douglas (1954), GM: Memories of George Moore (1956) and These Were the Hours (1965), a posthumously published memoir. She died in Paris in 1965.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Nancy Cunard, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to May 1999 have been organized into two series. Series I, Miriam J. Benkovitz Collection (1930-1965), contains letters from Cunard to Miriam Benkovitz, biographer and bibliographer of Ronald Firbank, Jinadasa Vijayatunga, and others, one letter from John Robert Scott to Cunard, holograph and typescript poems, articles and translations by Cunard, and a typescript memoir by Iris Tree inscribed to Cunard. Series II, Materials from Other Sources (1919-1948), contains holograph and typescript writings by Cunard.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Poetry -- Women authors; Poetry, Modern -- 20th Century; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Poetry; Authors; Poets; Beltrán, Neftalí; Benkovitz, Miriam J., 1911-; Cunard, Nancy, 1896-1965; Firbank, Ronald, 1886-1926; Scott, John Robertson; Tree, Iris, 1897-1968; Vijayatunga, J. (Jinadasa), 1902-
- Miriam J. Benkovitz Collection, 1930-1965; Series I; 0.2; (1/2 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Purchased from Swann Galleries, 1986, on the Albert H. Childs Fund, from the collection of Miriam J. Benkovitz
  - LETTERS FROM NANCY CUNARD
    - Benkovitz, Miriam J., 1954-64, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
      Includes: "White Hall Hotels, London Weekly Diary of Social Events," October 19-25, 1958
    - Carroll, John, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [Firbank?], Ronald, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gawsworth, John, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Removed from: Pensées en Tunisie by John Gawsworth
    - Heinemann (Firm). Copy of letter, 1954 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - [Lehmann], John, [n.y.] Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes: Copy of a letter from Robert Weinberger to the Guardian (Manchester, England)
    - Moult, Thomas, [n.y.] Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Patmore, Derek, 1965 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes: Two poems by Cunard entitled "The Great Hall" and "Brigit," typescripts, 1964
    - [Quennell], Peter, 1957 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Scott, John Robertson, [1944?] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Turner, W. J. (Walter James), 1937 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Vijayatunga, J. (Jinadasa), 1964-65 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified, 1930 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - LETTERS TO NANCY CUNARD
    - Scott, John Robertson, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - WRITINGS BY NANCY CUNARD
    - General Writings
      - "Copy of a recent article for England (Travelogue)," typescript article, corrected (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - "Incarnations," typescript poem, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - "Noël, Amour, Guerre 1944," typescript poem, 1944-45 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - "Thoughts About Ronald Firbank," typescript, corrected, 1954 Nov (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Translations of Works by Others
      - "Arbres," typescript copy and translation of a poem by "Geraldine", 1949 Jan (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - "Soneto en Yucatán," holograph copy and translation of a poem by Neftalí Beltrán, 1948[?] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Tree, Iris. "We Shall Not Forget," typescript memoir, corrected and inscribed to Nancy Cunard (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Materials from Other Sources, 1919-1948; Series II; 0.2; (1/2 box)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - LETTERS FROM NANCY CUNARD
    - Tzara, Tristan, [n.y.] Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - WRITINGS BY NANCY CUNARD
    - "Ballad of the Two Wars," typescript poem, corrected. Inscribed to Langston Hughes, 1937 Aug (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "In Answer to a Reproof," holograph poem, 1919 Jul (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "Londres, Été 48," holograph article, [1948 Jul?] (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Includes: Letter on verso of last page from Cunard to Walter [Strachan?], and a typescript English translation
    - "Three parts from the long epic poem on Spain," typescript, corrected. Inscribed to Langston Hughes, 1946 Sep (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Restricted Fragile
  Restricted Fragile materials may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 5 (Box port, Folder 36)
  - Box 1, folder 8 (Box port, Folder 37)
  - Box 1, folder 10 (Box port, Folder 38)
  - Box 1, folder 24 (Box port, Folder 39)
  - Box 1, folder 28 (Box port, Folder 40)
  - Box 1, folder 35 (Box port, Folder 41)